Guide to the Frank Joseph Kottke Papers 1936-1994
Washington State University Libraries Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections
Frank Joseph Kottke papers
1936-1994
Washington State University Libraries, Manuscripts, Archives and Special Collections
Kottke, Frank Joseph
Cage 823
4.0 linear feet 8 boxes
The Frank Joseph Kottke Papers consists of materials correspondence and other records created and collected by Kottke over his adult life. The collection includes correspondence with his family during World War II, records generated from his position on the Citizen's Advisory Committee for Pullman Public Transit, and letters to Washington state politicians in the United States legislature. Dr. Kottke was a professor of economics at Washington State University from 1961-1979.
Frank Kottke (1913-2002) was a Professor of Economics at Washington State University (WSU) from 1961-1979. Kottke, who was born in Chicago, Illinois, earned his PhD from Columbia University in 1940, was drafted by the Army in 1943, taught at the University of North Carolina from 1946-1951 and worked for the Federal Trade Commission as an expert in competition and monopolies. After joining WSU's faculty in 1961, Kottke taught courses in industrial organization.
In 1938, Dr. Kottke met Dr. Esther Hendee (1903-1974) and the two began a relationship. Like Kottke, Dr. Hendee was highly educated. She earned a PhD in biology from University of California, Berkeley and was working at Russell Sage College, an all-women’s school in Troy, New York. The two married in the fall of 1939 and had their first child, Margaret, in April of 1943. They remained married until Esther’s death in 1974.
Kottke retired from WSU in 1979 and served on the Citizen's Advisory Committee for Pullman Public Transit in the 1980s and 1990s. Kottke moved to Spokane in 1994, where he passed away in 2002.
This collection consists of three distinct sets of materials related to Frank Kottke's role as a member of the Citizen's Advisory Committee for Pullman Public Transit, as a citizen informing U.S. senators and representatives on his position on matters of public policy, and as a husband writing his wife during his time with the Army during World War II. This collection contains correspondence, minutes and reports related to public transportation in Pullman, Washington, and clippings informing his public policy letters to U.S. political figures.
This collection is arranged into three series.
Series 1: Pullman Transit Citizen's Advisory Committee, 1985-1993. This series consists of papers relating to Kottke's position on the Citizen's Advisory Committee (CAC) for public transportation in Pullman from 1985-1993 and has been divided into two subseries.
Subseries 1: Meetings, 1988-1993. This subseries contains minutes and reports from CAC meetings and is arranged in reverse chronological order.
Subseries 2: Subject files, 1984-1990. consists of special reports, correspondence, budgets, and surveys on topics including bus fare, routes, ads on buses, Americans with Disabilities Act compliance, student ridership, and a taxi service run by Pullman Transit. This subseries is organized alphabetically by the subject headings Kottke devised.
Series 2: Public policy correspondence, 1975-1994. This series consists of correspondence about public policy to members of the U.S. House and Senate from 1975-1994. These letters cover a wide range of topics from taxes and deficits to Medicare and Social Security to Anti-Trust Law and banking. It contains a number of responses from the offices of Washington state politicians, including Representative Thomas Foley, Senator Brock Adams, Senator Patty Murray, and Governor Booth Gardner. It also includes articles collected by Kottke related to the topics discussed. This series had been organized by Dr. Kottke and is arranged in reverse chronological order.
Series 3: Personal correspondence, 1936-1946. This series consists of the personal correspondence of Frank Kottke from 1938-1945. It includes incoming and outgoing letters between Kottke, his family and his fiancée Esther C. Hendee, who became his wife during the course of this correspondence. These letters fall into two categories: the initial exchanges between Frank and Esther during the months leading up to their marriage and letters to Frank from Esther and his family during Frank’s time in the Army (1943-1945). The latter correspondence includes commentary on wartime life, long distance relationships, and anecdotes and updates about their daughter Margaret. The letters reveal the initial apprehensions that both Frank and Esther felt regarding their age difference, thoughts concerning women in the workforce, and opinions about appropriate gender roles in 1940s America. Unlike the rest of the collection, the correspondence was not completely sorted by Dr. Kottke and its arrangement diverges significantly from its original order. The second folder includes an introduction by Dr. Kottke explaining his attempts to arrange the letters and his initial feelings regarding Esther written in 1980. This series is arranged chronologically.
This collection is open and available for research use.
The Frank Joseph Kottke Papers were donated to Washington State University by Kottke in 1993 and 1994 (MS 1993.23 and MS 1994.30). A latter accession was donated by Brigham Young University-Idaho archivist Martin Raish in 2011 (MS 2011.29). Raish came by a body of correspondence to Kottke and his wife Esther via his neighbor who purchased the letters from a second hand dealer.
Kottke provided an oral history for the Centennial Oral History Project (UA 202) in 1987. The interview may be viewed on the MASC Digital Collections website.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Kottke, Frank Joseph.
Hendee, Esther C. (Esther Crissey), 1903-.; Washington State University--Faculty--Archives.; Economics teachers -- 20th century--Washington (State)--Pullman--Archives.; Local transit--Washington (State)--Pullman.; World War, 1939-1945.; Love letters.
Transportation.; Home and Family.; Politics and Politicians.; Washington (State).
- Pullman Transit Citizen's Advisory Committee, 1985-1993; Series 1
  - Meetings, 1988-1993; Subseries 1
    - Meeting, March 25, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Meeting, December 17, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Meeting, October 1992 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Meeting, May 28, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Meeting, April 16, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Special meeting on six year plan, March 4, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Meeting, February 20, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Americans with Disabilities Act hearing, January 16, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Meeting, December 1991 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Meeting, October 17, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Meeting, August 22, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Meeting, June 20, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Meeting, April 1991 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Meeting, February 6, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Meeting, December 20, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Meeting, October 10, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Meeting, August 8, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Meeting, May 16, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Pullman Transit Annual Report, May 1990 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Meeting, April 11, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Meeting, February 7, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Meeting, December 1989 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Meeting, October 11, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Meeting, August 9, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Meeting, February - May 1989 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Pullman Transit Annual Report, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Meeting, November 1988 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Meeting, April 1988 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Backup data for meeting, April 1988 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Subject files, 1988-1993; Subseries 2
    - Backup data for meeting, April 1988 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Advertisements on buses, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Budgets, 1984-1987 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Bus purchase, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Bus storage, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Capital improvements program, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Charters, 1986-1988 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Data for WSU student body impact on transit, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Dial-a-Ride, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Faculty parking, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Fare - late night express, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Goals, 1984-1986 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Pullman Transit Annual Report, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Pullman Transit Annual Report, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Pullman Transit commission, 1986-1988 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Pullman Transit development plan, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Pullman Transit system review, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Ridership, 1984-1987 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Small bus, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Taxi, 1984-1988 (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - WSU student cost and input, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 49)
- Public policy correspondence, 1975-1994; Series 2
  - Public policy correspondence, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Public policy correspondence, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Public policy correspondence, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Public policy correspondence, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Public policy correspondence, May - December 1990 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Public policy correspondence, January - April 1990 (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Public policy correspondence, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - Pullman cable television correspondence, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - Public policy correspondence, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - Public policy correspondence, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 59)
  - Public policy correspondence, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 60)
  - Amendments to antitrust laws, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 61)
  - Public policy correspondence, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 62)
  - Public policy correspondence, 1983-1984 (Box 4, Folder 63)
  - Public policy correspondence, 1981-1982 (Box 4, Folder 64)
  - Public policy correspondence, 1975-1980 (Box 4, Folder 65)
- Personal correspondence, 1936-1946; Series 3
  - Incoming correspondence to Esther Hendee, 1936-1944 (Box 5, Folder 66)
  - Correspondence, December 1938 (Box 5, Folder 67)
  - Correspondence, January 1939 (Box 5, Folder 68)
  - Correspondence, February 1939 (Box 5, Folder 69)
  - Correspondence, March 1939 (Box 5, Folder 70)
  - Correspondence, April 1939 (Box 5, Folder 71)
  - Correspondence, May 1939 (Box 5, Folder 72)
  - Correspondence, June 1939 (Box 5, Folder 73)
  - Correspondence, July 1939 (Box 5, Folder 74)
  - Correspondence, August 1939 (Box 5, Folder 75)
  - Correspondence, September 1939 (Box 5, Folder 76)
  - Correspondence, October 1939 (Box 6, Folder 77)
  - Correspondence, November 1939 (Box 6, Folder 78)
  - Correspondence, December 1939 (Box 6, Folder 79)
  - Correspondence, January 1940 (Box 6, Folder 80)
  - Correspondence, November 1941 (Box 6, Folder 81)
  - Correspondence, December 1942 (Box 6, Folder 82)
  - Correspondence, circa January - March 1943 (Box 6, Folder 83)
  - Correspondence, January 1943 (Box 6, Folder 84)
  - Correspondence, February 1943 (Box 6, Folder 85)
  - Correspondence, March 1943 (Box 6, Folder 86)
  - Correspondence, April 1943 (Box 6, Folder 87)
  - Correspondence, May 1943 (Box 6, Folder 88)
  - Correspondence, June 1943 (Box 6, Folder 89)
  - Correspondence, July 1943 (Box 6, Folder 90)
  - Correspondence, August 1943 (Box 6, Folder 91)
  - Correspondence, September 1943 (Box 6, Folder 92)
  - Correspondence, October 1943 (Box 6, Folder 93)
  - Correspondence, November 1943 (Box 6, Folder 94)
  - Correspondence, December 1943 (Box 6, Folder 95)
  - Correspondence, January 1944 (Box 6, Folder 96)
  - Correspondence, March 1944 (Box 6, Folder 97)
  - Correspondence, April 1944 (Box 6, Folder 98)
  - Correspondence, May 1944 (Box 6, Folder 99)
  - Correspondence, June 1944 (Box 7, Folder 100)
  - Correspondence, July 1944 (Box 7, Folder 101)
  - Correspondence, August 1944 - November 1944 (Box 7, Folder 102)
  - Correspondence, December 1 - 19, 1944 (Box 7, Folder 103)
  - Correspondence, December 20 - 31, 1944 (Box 7, Folder 104)
  - Correspondence, January 1 - 15, 1945 (Box 7, Folder 105)
  - Correspondence, January 16 - 31, 1945 (Box 7, Folder 106)
  - Correspondence, February 1 - 14, 1945 (Box 7, Folder 107)
  - Correspondence, February 15 - 28, 1945 (Box 7, Folder 108)
  - Correspondence, March 1945 (Box 7, Folder 109)
  - Correspondence, April 1 - 15, 1945 (Box 8, Folder 110)
  - Correspondence, April 16 - 30, 1945 (Box 8, Folder 111)
  - Correspondence, May 1945 (Box 8, Folder 112)
  - Correspondence, June 1945 (Box 8, Folder 113)
  - Correspondence, July - September 1945 (Box 8, Folder 114)
  - Correspondence, October - December 1945 (Box 8, Folder 115)
  - Correspondence, January 1946 (Box 8, Folder 116)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, undated (Box 8, Folder 117)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, undated (Box 8, Folder 118)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, undated (Box 8, Folder 119)